Guide to the Gary Huck and Mike Konopacki Labor Cartoons Collection WAG.264
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Gary Huck and Mike Konopacki Labor Cartoons Collection
1982-2018
1985-2010
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Huck/Konopacki labor cartoons
Konopacki, Mike
Huck, Gary
Funke, Michael
WAG.264
40.75 Linear Feet in 7 record cartons, 2 half manuscript boxes, and 33 oversize flat boxes
This collection contains thousands of illustrated and computer generated political cartoons by Gary Huck and Mike Konopacki in addition to business records and background subject files for their labor cartooning partnership--the core of which is their subscription service of monthly packets of labor cartoons. In 1983, Gary Huck and Mike Konopacki created Huck/Konopacki Labor Cartoons, syndicating their cartoons to the labor press in the U.S. and Canada. Collectively, their work covers labor movements, strikes and injustices across the country, often focusing on Wisconsin politics and teachers.
Accruals
The donors have scheduled annual donations of labor packets, preparatory materials, and business records. These materials will be added to Series 3 and 4, continuing the chronological order of the series.
Immediate Source of Aquisition
The initial donation was made by the artists, Gary Huck and Mike Konopacki, in 2003. The accession numbers associated with this gift are 2003.034 and 2003.035. The collaborative labor packets, preparatory materials, and business correspondence were received in several batches in subsequent. The accession numbers associated with these gifts are 2013.020, 2014.142, 2014.157, 2015.045, 2016.031, 2017.034, 2019.008, and 2019.084.
Several signed drawings by Gary Huck were donated by Michael Funke in 2016. The accession number associated with this gift is 2017.041.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Arrangement
The collection has been arranged into four series as follows:
Series 1: Gary Huck Cartoons, Series 2: Mike Konopacki Cartoons, Series 3: Labor Cartoon Packets, Series 4: Huck/Konopacki Labor Cartoons Records
Series 1 and 2 are arranged chronologically. Series 3 and 4 are arranged alphabetically and subsequently by date.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains thousands of illustrated and computer generated political cartoons by Gary Huck and Mike Konopacki, in addition to business records and background subject files for their labor cartooning partnership--the core of which is their subscription service of monthly packets of labor cartoons.
The artists employed many different materials and supplies, which evolved as they learned and incorporated new techniques into their cartoons. The collection contains preparatory tracings, illustrations, and computer generated graphics.
The cartoons in Series 1-3 focus on union activity, corporate greed, Wisconsin and national politicians, women's rights and social justice. The teachers cartoon package was added later as an additional service and included four additional cartoons in each monthly packet. Also included in the labor packets is a series called Women Workers' History, that was originally created by Gary Huck for the United Electrical, Radio and Machine Workers of America (U.E.) News. It is divided into more than 100 "chapters" on different events, topics, and individuals, and accompanied by photographs or period style drawings with captions and cartoon balloons offering humorous comments from the participants. The series ran in the labor packets for ten years, beginning in 1987; it was repeated in its entirety in the packets from 1997 through 2006, and began its third cycle in 2007. Most cartoons in Series 1-3 were created for the distributed monthly packets of cartoons, but the collection also includes some that were created to be used in separate projects, including books and campaigns, and for individual labor unions; information on many of these other projects and clients may be found in Series 4.
Historical/Biographical Note
Mike Konopacki (1951- ) began labor cartooning for the student newspaper at the University of Wisconsin-Madison where he majored in political science. Later, he cartooned for the Madison Press Connection, a local Wisconsin daily created by striking newspaper workers in 1978, while driving buses for Madison Metro. Konpacki has also collaborated with writer Alec Dubro to write and illustrate several comic books. He was the co-author and illustrator for Howard Zinn's A People's History of the American Empire. Konopacki also works on web-based cartoons and animations, specializing in satire and corporate images and logos.
Gary Huck drew cartoons for Racine Labor in the 1970s, the longest domestic labor weekly in the US. He has been the political cartoonist for the United Electrical, Radio and Machine Workers of America (UE) in Pittsburg, PA since 1985, when he succeeded Fred Wright. Huck is the only full-time cartoonist employed by a union in the U.S. He is also the cartoon curator and graphic designer for arts group ArtUp. Huck was responsible for the Women's Workers' History column, which originally appeared in the UE News and was later reproduced for the Huck/Konopacki syndicated cartoon service, distributed as packets of cartoons.
In 1983 he and Konopacki created Huck/Konopacki Labor Cartoons, syndicating their cartoons to the labor press in the U.S. and Canada. Together, they have worked on six publications entitled Bye! American, THEM, MAD in USA, Working Class Hero, Two Headed Space Alien Shrinks Labor Movement and American Dread. Huck and Konopacki have different styles of drawing and use a variety of materials in their work. They have used ink, crayon, line screens, zip tones, and computer generated graphics. Their cartoons collectively cover labor movements, strikes and injustices across the country, often focusing on Wisconsin politics and teachers.
Audiovisual Access Policies and Procedures
Audiovisual materials have not been preserved and may not be available to researchers. Materials not yet digitized will need to have access copies made before they can be used. To request an access copy, or if you are unsure if an item has been digitized, please contact tamiment.wagner@nyu.edu, (212) 998-2630 with the collection name, collection number, and a description of the item(s) requested. A staff member will respond to you with further information.
Cartoonists -- United States; Strikes and lockouts -- Cartoonists -- United States.; Labor movements -- Political aspects -- United States -- Caricatures and cartoons; Wisconsin; Caricatures and cartoons.; Political cartoons -- United States.; Political cartoons.; Politics and culture -- Wisconsin.; Wisconsin -- Politics and government.; Caricatures and cartoons -- United States.; Konopacki, Mike; Huck, Gary; Funke, Michael
- Series I: Gary Huck Cartoons
  - Political Cartoons, 1982-1986 (Box 1, Folder 1-22)
  - Political Cartoons, 1986 (Box Shared Tamiment MSXOS001, Folder 1)
  - Political Cartoons, 1986-1988 (Box 2, Folder 1-22)
  - Political Cartoons, 1987 (Box Shared Tamiment MSXOS001, Folder 1)
  - Political Cartoons, 1988-1989 (Box 3, Folder 1-19)
  - Political Cartoons, 1989 (Box 4, Folder 1-17)
  - Political Cartoons, 1989-1990 (Box 5, Folder 1-14)
  - Political Cartoons, 1990 (Box 6, Folder 1-12)
  - Political Cartoons, 1991 (Box 7, Folder 1-14)
  - Political Cartoons, 1991 (Box 8, Folder 1-17)
  - Political Cartoons, 1992-1993 (Box 9, Folder 1-14)
  - Political Cartoons, 1993-1995, undated (Box 10, Folder 1-13)
  - Political Cartoons: Oil Logos, 1987-1991; 2014.157 (Box 38, Folder 19)
  - Political Cartoons: Gifts to Michael Funke, 1985-1990 (Box 38, Folder 20)
  - Political Cartoons (Oversize), 1984-1985 (Box 39, Folder 1)
- Series II: Mike Konopacki Cartoons
  - Political Cartoons, Dec 1984 - Aug 1985 (Box 11, Folder 1-15)
  - Political Cartoons, Sep 1985 - May 1986 (Box 12, Folder 1-15)
  - Political Cartoons, Jun 1986 - Dec 1986 (Box 13, Folder 1-13)
  - Political Cartoons, 1987 (Box 14, Folder 1-14)
  - Political Cartoons, 1988 (Box 15, Folder 1-17)
  - Political Cartoons, 1988 (Box 16, Folder 1-8)
  - Political Cartoons, 1988-1989 (Box 17, Folder 1-14)
  - Political Cartoons, 1989-1991 (Box 18, Folder 1-17)
  - Political Cartoons, 1991 (Box 19, Folder 1-11)
  - Political Cartoons, 1991-1992 (Box 20, Folder 1-8)
  - Political Cartoons, 1992 (Box 21, Folder 1-6)
  - Political Cartoons, 1993-1994 (Box 22, Folder 1-6)
  - Political Cartoons, 1995-1998, undated (Box 23, Folder 1-11)
  - Political Cartoons, undated (Box 24, Folder 1-12)
  - Political Cartoons (Oversize), 1980s-1990s, undated (Box 39, Folder 1-2, Box 40, Folder 5, Box 41)
- Series III: Labor Cartoon Packets
  - Labor Packets, 1983-1994 (Box 25, Folder 1-108)
  - Labor Packets, Nov 1990 - Dec 1990 (Box 31, Folder 15)
  - Labor Packets, Jan 1995 - Jul 2002 (Box 26, Folder 1-93)
  - Labor Packets, Aug 2002 - Dec 2011 (Box 27, Folder 1-109)
  - Labor Packets, 2012 (Box 37, Folder 1-12)
  - Labor Packets, 2013; 2014.142 (Box 37, Folder 13-16)
  - Labor Packets, 2014 (Box 37, Folder 17-18)
  - Labor Packets, 2015 (Box 37, Folder 19-21)
  - Labor Packets, 2016 (Box 37, Folder 46-49)
  - Labor Packets, 2017 (Box 40, Folder 1-3)
  - Labor Packets, 2018 (Box 42, Folder 2-4)
  - Labor Packets: Freedom of Speech, 1989-1991 (Box 27, Folder 110)
  - Labor Packets: Healthcare, 1994-2001 (Box 27, Folder 111)
  - Labor Packets: Organizing Cartoons, 1990-1997 (Box 27, Folder 112)
  - Labor Packets: Organizing Cartoons, 1992-1997 (Box 27, Folder 113)
  - Labor Packets: September 11, 2001, 2001-2002 (Box 27, Folder 114)
  - Labor Packets: Staley, A.E., 1993 (Box 27, Folder 115)
  - Labor Packets: Cartoons for Auction, Labor Day, 1991-1996 (Box 28, Folder 1)
  - Labor Packets: Cartoons for Auction, Labor Day, 1991-1996 (Box 28, Folder 2)
  - Labor Packets: Tracings, circa 1988-1994 (Box 28, Folder 3)
  - Labor Packets: Tracings, 2003-2005 (Box 28, Folder 4-25)
  - Labor Packets: Tracings, 2007-2010 (Box 29, Folder 1-33)
  - Labor Packets: Tracings, 2011 (Box 30, Folder 1-9)
  - Labor Packets: Tracings, 2012 (Box 38, Folder 1-9)
  - Labor Packets: Tracings, 2013; 2014.142 (Box 38, Folder 10-12)
  - Labor Packets: Tracings, 2014 (Box 38, Folder 13-15)
  - Labor Packets: Tracings, 2015 (Box 38, Folder 16-18)
  - Labor Packets: Tracings, 2016 (Box 37, Folder 42-45)
  - Labor Packets: Tracings, 2017 (Box 40, Folder 4)
  - Labor Packerts: Tracings, 2018 (Box 42, Folder 1)
  - Labor Packets: Tracings: Capitalism Sucks, circa 2000s (Box 30, Folder 10)
  - Labor Packets: Tracings: Konopacki, circa 1980s-2000s (Box 30, Folder 11-22)
  - Labor Packets: Tracings: Konopacki, circa 1980s-2000s (Box 31, Folder 1-6)
  - Labor Packets: Tracings: Konopacki, 1997 (Box 31, Folder 7)
  - Labor Packets: Tracings: Konopacki, 2000 (Box 31, Folder 8)
  - Labor Packets: Tracings: Konopacki, 2001 (Box 31, Folder 9)
  - Labor Packets: Tracings: Konopacki, undated (Box 31, Folder 10-12)
  - Labor Packets: Tracings: Wage Gap, 2000 (Box 31, Folder 13-14)
- Series IV: Huck/Konopacki Labor Cartoons Records
  Scope and Content Note
  Series 4 contains the files for the Huck/Konopacki Labor Cartoons and mostly relate to the subscriptions and syndication of this collborative business. These records were primarily compiled by Mike Konopacki and reflect many of his individual projects and interests. Of particular interest is the United Food and Commercial Workers (UFCW) Local P-9 Hormel strike of 1985-86 in Austin, Minnesota and the A.E. Staley Allied Industrial Workers Local 837 workers lockout of 1993. Konopacki produced a weekly newsletter for locked out Staley workers entitled the War Zone Report.
  This series also includes projects and artwork created for advertising leaflets, local union actitivies, published and unpublished manuscripts, and campaigns. Series 4 is arranged alphabetically and then by date.
  - Correspondence, 1989-2011, undated (Box 32, Folder 1-23)
  - Correspondence (includes postcard from Pete Seeger and letter from Senator Carol Mosely-Braun), 1990-1996; 2014.157 (Box 37, Folder 22)
  - Correspondence, 1996 (Box 37, Folder 23)
  - Correspondence, 2007 (Box 37, Folder 24)
  - Correspondence, 2010 (Box 37, Folder 25)
  - Correspondence, 2012 (Box 37, Folder 26)
  - Correspondence, 2013; 2014.142 (Box 37, Folder 27)
  - Correspondence, 2014 (Box 37, Folder 28)
  - Correspondence, 2015 (Box 37, Folder 29)
  - Correspondence: Books Orders, 2003-2004 (Box 32, Folder 24)
  - Correspondence: Cancellations, 1984-2010 (Box 33, Folder 1-24)
  - Correspondence: Cancellations, 2012 (Box 37, Folder 30-33)
  - Correspondence: Cancellations: Teachers, 1992 (Box 33, Folder 25)
  - Correspondence: Cancellations: Teachers, 1993 (Box 33, Folder 26)
  - Correspondence: George Meany, 1993-1994 (Box 33, Folder 27)
  - Correspondence: Hate Mail: Kiegson Election, 1984 (Box 33, Folder 28)
  - Correspondence: Konopacki, 1982-1988 (Box 33, Folder 29)
  - Correspondence: Impact Visuals: Promotional Materials, circa 1986 (Box 33, Folder 30)
  - Correspondence: Metzgar, Jack: World Trade and American Jobs, 1988-1989 (Box 33, Folder 31)
  - Correspondence: Metzgar, Jack: World Trade and American Jobs, 1988-1989 (Box 33, Folder 32)
  - Correspondence: Milwaukee Sentinel Case, 1986-1987 (Box 33, Folder 33)
  - Correspondence: The Newspaper Guild, 1989 (Box 33, Folder 34)
  - Correspondence: Patriot Act Exhibit, 2001-2002 (Box 33, Folder 35)
  - Correspondence: Teachers, 1992 (Box 33, Folder 36)
  - Correspondence: United Food and Commerical Workers Union: Austin Mural, 1986 (Box 33, Folder 37)
  - Correspondence: United Food and Commerical Workers Union: Austin Mural Removal, 1986 (Box 33, Folder 38)
  - Correspondence: United Food and Commerical Workers Union: Support Group, 1986 (Box 33, Folder 39)
  - Correspondence: United Mine Workers: Pittston Strike, 1989-1990 (Box 33, Folder 40)
  - Correspondence: Web Orders, Mar 2001 - Sep 2001 (Box 33, Folder 41)
  - Correspondence: Wright, Fred, 1984-1985 (Box 33, Folder 42)
  - Gary Huck Oil Logo Controversy, 1991, 2006; 2014.157 (Box 37, Folder 34)
  - Hightower Radio: Huck Konopack segment on Workplace Funnies, vol 1 and 2 (cassette tapes), undated; 2014.157 (Box 37, Folder 35)
  - Layout Boards, 1980s-1990s (Box 41, Folder 3)
  - Mailing Lists, 2003-2012 (Box 34, Folder 30-40)
  - Mailing Lists, 2013-2015 (Box 37, Folder 36-38)
  - Mailing Lists, 2016 (Box 37, Folder 50)
  - Photograph: Gary Huck, Lisa Canada, and Pete Seeger, undated; 2014.157 (Box 37, Folder 39)
  - Photographs: Gary Huck trip to Cuba for Exhibit of Huck/Konopacki Cartoons at the Museo del Humor, San Antonio de los Banos, Cuba, 1993; 2014.157 (Box 37, Folder 40)
  - Program Books: Political Cartoon Exhibits, 1998, 2004; 2014.157 (Box 37, Folder 41)
  - Projects: Association of Flight Attendants: Cartoon Development, 1987 (Box 35, Folder 1)
  - Projects: Bye American Book Development, 1981-1986 (Box 35, Folder 2)
  - Projects: Bye American Cartoon Exhibition, 1987 (Box 35, Folder 3)
  - Projects: Cartoons in Newsletters, 1982-1983 (Box 35, Folder 4)
  - Projects: Cartoons in Publications, 1980-1992 (Box 35, Folder 5)
  - Projects: Comics: Amnesty International, circa 2002 (Box 35, Folder 6)
  - Projects: Comics: Dubro and Konopacki Collaborations, 1990s-2000s (Box 35, Folder 7)
  - Projects: Comics: Patriot Act, 2002 (Box 35, Folder 8)
  - Projects: Comics: Public Services International, circa 2001 (Box 35, Folder 9)
  - Projects: Comics: Public Services International Sketches (Box 35, Folder 10)
  - Projects: Drug Wars Board Game, circa 1990s (Box 35, Folder 11)
  - Projects: Horatio Alger Graphics, 1999 (Box 35, Folder 12)
  - Projects: International Union of Electrical Workers News, 1979-1981 (Box 35, Folder 13)
  - Projects: Konopacki: Comics, 2000 (Box 35, Folder 14)
  - Projects: Konopacki: Comics, circa 2000 (Box 35, Folder 15)
  - Projects: Konopacki: Comics: Jobs with Justice (Box 35, Folder 16)
  - Projects: Konopacki: Comics: Connecticut Federation of Teachers, circa 1990s (Box 35, Folder 17)
  - Projects: Konopacki: Comics: Connecticut Federation of Teachers, circa 1998 (Box 35, Folder 18)
  - Projects: Konopacki: General, circa 1990s (Box 36, Folder 1)
  - Projects: Konopacki: Madison Teachers, Inc., 1993-1997 (Box 36, Folder 2)
  - Projects: Konopacki: Posters, 1990s (Box 36, Folder 3)
  - Projects: Konopacki: Sketches, circa 1990s-2000s (Box 36, Folder 4)
  - Projects: Konopacki: United Brotherhood of Carpenters and Joiners of America, 1987-1989 (Box 36, Folder 5-6)
  - Projects: Mad in the USA, 1993 (Box 36, Folder 7)
  - Projects: Overset, 1984 (Box 36, Folder 8)
  - Projects: Red the Anarchist Clown, 1994 (Box 36, Folder 9)
  - Projects: Stickin' to the Union Book Draft, 1986 (Box 36, Folder 10)
  - Projects: Teamsters Mother Earth, undated (Box 36, Folder 11)
  - Projects: Them Book Cartoons, 1987-1990 (Box 36, Folder 12-14)
  - Projects: United Food and Commercial Workers Union: Iowa Beef Processors, Inc Boycott, circa 1986 (Box 36, Folder 15)
  - Projects: United Food and Commercial Workers Union: Local P-9: Hormel Strike Fundraising Ad, 1986 (Box 36, Folder 16)
  - Projects: What's Left in Political Cartooning Exhibit, 1987-1988 (Box 36, Folder 17)
  - Promotional Materials: Brochures, circa 1984 (Box 36, Folder 18)
  - Promotional Materials: Brochure Development, circa 1985 (Box 36, Folder 18)
  - Promotional Materials: Subscription Advertisements, circa 1990s (Box 36, Folder 19)
  - Research: After School Day Care Fight, 1989 (Box 33, Folder 43)
  - Research: Association of American Editorial Cartoonists, 1990 (Box 33, Folder 44)
  - Research: Cartoon Censorship, 2001-2002 (Box 33, Folder 45)
  - Research: Computer Animation Course, circa 1995 (Box 33, Folder 46)
  - Research: Education Clippings, 1992 (Box 33, Folder 47)
  - Research: Edwin Meese III, General Attorney, 1988 (Box 33, Folder 48)
  - Research: General, 1988, 1994, undated (Box 33, Folder 49)
  - Research: Horatio Alger Award, 1994 (Box 33, Folder 50)
  - Research: Jobs Fraud, 1986-1988 (Box 33, Folder 51)
  - Research: Labor Articles, 1980s (Box 33, Folder 52)
  - Research: Labor News, 1990 (Box 33, Folder 53)
  - Research: Madison Community Foundation, 1993 (Box 33, Folder 54)
  - Research: Peace Net, 1990 (Box 33, Folder 55)
  - Research: Staley Manufacturing, 1992-1993 (Box 34, Folder 1)
  - Research: Stoughton Trailer Strike, 1984-1989 (Box 34, Folder 2)
  - Research: Teamster Flyers, circa 1990s (Box 34, Folder 3)
  - Research: United Brotherhood of Carpenters and Joiners of America, 1984-1989 (Box 34, Folder 4)
  - Research: United Brotherhood of Carpenters and Joiners of America: Hormel Strike, 1986 (Box 34, Folder 5)
  - Research: United Brotherhood of Carpenters and Joiners of America: Local P-9: Hormel Strike, 1986 (Box 34, Folder 7)
  - Research: United Brotherhood of Carpenters and Joiners of America: Jobs, 1987-1988 (Box 34, Folder 6)
  - Research: Wage Slave World News, 1989 (Box 34, Folder 8)
  - Research: War Zone Report Staley Workers, 1993 (Box 34, Folder 9)
  - Subscriptions, 1983-2003 (Box 34, Folder 10-30)